American Psychological Association Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Journals and Publications, 1925-1986 (Box 621-687)
  - Journals
    - Periodically
      - Issues and drafts
        - Chronological
          - Oct. 1972-Dec. 1975, (4 folders) (Box 680)
          - Jan. 1976-May 1978, (4 folders) (Box 681)
          - June 1978-Oct. 1979, (2 folders) (Box 682)
        - Printed
          - Volumes I-VIII, XI, 1971-1980, (2 folders)
          - Volume XII, 1981 (Box 683)
      - Reports to executives, 1977
      - Surveys
        - Gimmickry, 1976, (3 folders)
        - Text preference and evaluation, 1977 (Box 684)
    - Psychological Abstracts
      - Correspondence
        - Editor, 1949-1953
        - General, 1957-1970
      - Miscellany, 1947, 1950, 1957-1961, 1969, undated
    - Psychological Bulletin, 1952-1974
    - Psychological Monograph
      - Correspondence
        - Editors, 1950-1966
        - Expenses, 1951 (Box 685)
        - General, 1941-1975
    - Psychological Review, 1952-1964
    - Psychology Major
      - Book by Paul Woods
        - Background material, 1977-1979
        - Reviews, Education and Training Board
          - 1976-1978
          - Undated (Box 686)
      - Consultant agreement, Paul Woods, 1974-1975, undated
      - Correspondence, 1975-1978
    - Psychology Today
      - Acquisition information, 1982-1983, (2 folders)
      - Financial, 1982-1986
      - Report, proposed acquisition of Psychology Today, 1983 (Box 687)
    - Teaching of Psychology
      - Background material, 1979-1981
      - Correspondence, 1970-1981, (3 folders)
      - Originals, 1972-1981
- Affiliated Organizations, 1932-1984 (Box 688-718)
  Correspondence, memoranda, agenda, abstracts, minutes of meetings, lists, legislation, notices, ballots, bills, expense reports, newsletters, bylaws, certificates, programs, and miscellaneous material.
  Arranged by name of organization and therein alphabetically by administrative subheadings, subject files, or type of material.
  - American Association for Applied Psychology (Box 688)
    - Board of Governors
      - Correspondence, 1940-1945
      - Meetings, 1941-1943, undated
      - Memoranda, 1938-1945, (2 folders)
    - Boards, committees, and sections
      - Boards
        - Affiliates
          - 1938-1942
          - 1943-1945 (Box 689)
        - Editors, 1938-1945, (2 folders)
      - Committees
        - Auditing Committee, 1938, 1940-1945
        - Committee on Committees, 1943
        - Committee revisions, 1939-1941, undated
        - Constitutional Revision, 1940-1943
        - Definitions, 1937-1938
        - Election Committee, 1939-1944, undated (Box 690)
        - General, 1937-1944
        - Graduate student affiliation, 1940-1941, undated
        - Incorporation, 1938, undated
        - Intern Training, 1938-1942
        - Joint Constitutional Committee, 1943-1945, undated
        - Legislation, 1939-1945
        - Meetings, agendas and minutes, 1937-1944
        - Membership matters, 1937-1942, undated
        - Miscellany, 1937-1942, undated (Box 691)
        - Non-member Participation, 1942-1943
        - Official Journal, 1944-1945
        - Phi Delta Kappa, Dictionary of Education, 1940-1944, undated
        - Professional Employment, 1937-1944
        - Professional Ethics, 1938-1941
        - Professional Training in Clinical Psychology, 1939-1945, (2 folders)
        - Program, 1942 (Box 692)
        - Psychological Backgrounds of Adult Education, 1943-1944
        - Psychological Clinic, 1937
        - Psychological Service in Schools and Institutions for Mental Defectives, 1938-1940, undated
        - Psychological Work in Institutions for Delinquent Boys and Girls, 1938-1942, undated
        - Public Relations, 1940-1943
        - Refugee Children, 1940-1942, undated
        - Relations with Social Workers, 1938-1945
        - Relations with the Educational Profession, 1939-1944 (Box 693)
        - Relations with the Engineering Profession, 1940-1943
        - Relations with the Library Profession, 1939-1943
        - Relations with the Medical Profession, 1939-1944, undated
        - Standardized Tests, 1938-1944
        - Standards for Psychological Service Centers, 1945
        - Technical Exhibit for the New York World's Fair, New York, N.Y. (1939), 1937-1940
        - Technical Manuals, 1937-1941
        - Title and Content of Courses, 1941-1943
        - Working Conditions, 1938-1941
      - Sections (Box 694)
        - Business and Industrial Section, 1939-1945, undated
        - Clinical Section
          - Correspondence, 1939-1944
          - Executive Committee, notices, 1938-1941, undated
          - General, 1938-1945, undated, (2 folders)
          - Memoranda, 1938-1941, undated
          - Minutes, 1937-1944
          - Nomination of Members of the Clinical Section for the Board of Editors of the American Association for Applied Psychology, 1939-1940, undated
          - Publications, 1937-1943, undated
          - Report of secretary, 1938-1940
          - State and regional associations, 1938-1940
        - Consulting, 1939-1946, undated (Box 695)
        - Educational, 1937-1945, (2 folders)
        - Industrial
          - American Association for Applied Psychology and APA merger, 1939-1942
          - APA publicity, 1943-1944, undated
          - Applications for membership, 1944, undated
          - Ballots, 1943-1944, undated
          - Correspondence (Box 696)
            - Chronological, 1938-1944, (2 folders)
            - Name file, B. Dvorak, 1945
        - Military, 1943-1945
    - Executive officers file
      - Executive secretary
        - Correspondence
          - English, Horace B., 1937-1939
          - Louttit, C. M.
            - General, 1939-1942
            - Louttit/English, 1939-1941
          - Bryan, Alice I., 1942-1946
      - Presidents
        - Correspondence
          - Fryer, Douglas, 1937-1938
          - Paterson, Donald Gildersleeve, 1938-1939
          - Doll, Edgar A., 1940-1941 (Box 697)
          - Bingham, Walter U., 1941
          - Louttit, C. M., 1942-1944
          - Poffenberger, A. T., 1944
          - Rogers, Carl R., 1944-1945
      - Treasurer
        - Accounts, 1940-1944
        - Correspondence
          - Greene, E. B., 1937-1938
          - Dunlap, Jack W., 1938-1941
          - Kurtz, Albert K., 1941-1942
          - Bills, Marion A., 1942-1946
    - Meetings, 1939-1944, (5 folders) (Box 698)
    - Miscellany
      - Bills and expenses, 1939-1943, undated
      - Circular letters to secretaries, 1940-1945, undated
      - Forms, 1943-1946, undated
      - Miscellaneous material, 1937-1944, undated
      - Newsletters, 1941-1943
    - Subject file
      - Abstracts
        - General, and applications, 1945, undated
        - Papers, 1939-1941
      - American Association for an International Office of Education, 1944
      - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1938-1945
      - American Psychological Association, 1937-1945 (Box 699)
      - Annual meetings, 1938-1947, (2 folders)
      - Applications
        - Rejected, 1938-1939
        - Votes, 1937-1940
      - Applied Psychology Monographs, 1942-1945 (Box 700)
      - Association of Consulting Psychologists, newsletters and report, 1935-1939
      - Association properties, 1941-1943
      - Bulletin series, 1939-1944
      - Bylaws
        - General, 1937-1946
        - Sections, 1938-1940, undated
      - Certificates, 1940-1942
      - Cleveland meeting, Cleveland, Ohio, Sept. 1944
      - Clinical certification, 1940-1944, undated
      - Clinics, lists, 1943
      - Corporation, 1937-1944
      - Council on Human Relations, 1941-1944
      - Directory (Box 701)
        - General, 1939-1945, undated
        - Listings, 1940-1941
      - Elections, 1938-1945
      - Emergency Committee, 1940-1945
      - The Fields of Applied Psychology, survey report, 1939
      - Inquiries, 1940-1945
      - Instruction in applied psychology, 1938-1944
      - Intersociety Constitutional Convention
        - Correspondence
          - 1942
          - 1943-1944 (Box 702)
        - Meeting, 29-31 May 1943
          - General, 1943
          - Minutes and reports, 1943
      - Journal of Applied Psychology, 1942-1944
      - Journal of Consulting psychology, 1939-1945, (2 folders)
      - Layman-Carter proposal, 1941, undated (Box 703)
      - Letterheads, 1938-1945, undated
      - Licensing, 1932-1944, undated
      - Mailing permits, 1939-1945
      - Meetings, time and place, 1941-1942
      - Membership
        - Applications, rejected, 1938-1943
        - Circular, 1942-1945
        - Correspondence, 1938-1947, (2 folders)
        - General, 1939-1941
        - Individuals, 1939-1945
        - Inquiries, 1939-1944 (Box 704)
        - Life, 1941-1943
        - Lists
          - American Association for Applied Psychology, 1939-1944, undated
          - APA divisions, 1946
          - Clinical Section, 1938-1946, undated
      - Metropolitan New York Association for Applied Psychology, 1940, 1942-1944
      - Military, 1938-1942, undated
      - National Committee for Mental Hygiene, 1941-1946
      - National Conference of Social Work, 1938-1946
      - National Council of Women Psychologists, 1941-1943
      - National Council on Rehabilitation, 1944-1945
      - National Research Council
        - Committee on History of Psychology and the Wars, 1944
        - General, 1941-1945
        - Office of Psychological Personnel, 1942-1945 (Box 705)
      - National Vocational Guidance Association, 1939-1940
      - New York State Association of Applied Psychologists, 1937-1944
      - Official delegates, 1941-1946
      - Pre-adoption tests, 1942-1944
      - Private practice, 1942
      - Professional standards and ethics, 1939-1941
      - Promotion, 1941, undated
      - Psychologists League, 1938-1939
      - Publications, 1937-1942, undated
      - Recommendations and proposals, 1937-1943
      - Rochester, N. Y., Guidance Center, 1940
      - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues, 1937-1943, undated
      - Survey and Planning Committee, 1942-1943
  - Conference of State Psychological Associations (Box 706)
    - General correspondence
      - 1946-1954, (9 folders)
      - 1955-1958, (3 folders) (Box 707)
    - State and regional file
      - Alabama, 1958
      - Alaska, 1958
      - Arizona, 1958
      - Arkansas, 1956-1958
      - California, 1948-1958
      - Colorado, 1958
      - Connecticut, 1944-1952
      - Delaware, 1950
      - District of Columbia, 1943-1958
      - Florida, 1948-1958
      - Georgia, 1947-1948 (Box 708)
      - Hawaii, 1958
      - Idaho, 1954-1958
      - Illinois, 1942-1958, (2 folders)
      - Indiana, 1942-1958
      - Iowa, 1955-1958
      - Kansas, 1953-1958
      - Kentucky, 1948-1958
      - Louisiana, 1953-1958
      - Maine, 1952-1958 (Box 709)
      - Maryland, 1956-1958
      - Massachusetts, 1953-1958
      - Michigan, 1952-1958
      - Midwestern Psychological Association, 1945-1947
      - Minnesota, 1952-1958
      - Mississippi, 1957-1958
      - Missouri, 1947-1958
      - Montana, 1958
      - Nebraska, 1957-1958
      - New Hampshire, 1953-1958
      - New Jersey
        - 1944-1949
        - 1950-1958 (Box 710)
      - New Mexico, 1956-1958
      - New York, 1943-1958, (2 folders)
      - North Carolina, 1952-1956
      - North Dakota, 1957-1958, 1977-1978
      - Ohio, 1957-1958
      - Oklahoma, 1957-1958
      - Ontario, Canada, 1955-1958
      - Oregon, 1957-1958, 1976, 1983
      - Pennsylvania, 1940-1958
      - Puerto Rico, 1953
      - Rhode Island, 1956-1958 (Box 711)
      - South Carolina, 1954-1958
      - South Dakota, 1957-1958
      - Tennessee, 1953-1958
      - Texas, 1956-1958
      - Utah, 1952-1958
      - Vermont, 1957-1958
      - Washington, 1954-1958, 1977
      - West Virginia, 1952-1958
      - Wisconsin, 1952-1958
      - Wyoming, 1957-1958
    - Subject file
      - American Psychologist, "Psychology in the States," 1954-1957, (2 folders)
      - Annual meeting, minutes, 1948-1957
      - Ballots, chairman and Council of Representative, 1956
      - Board of Examiners, 1956
      - Board of Professional Affairs, 1958
      - Bylaws, 1956 (Box 712)
      - Convention program, 1956-1957
      - Council of Representatives, 1947-1956
      - Division of Clinical and Abnormal Psychology, 1952-1954
      - Executive Committee
        - Correspondence, 1954-1957
        - Minutes, 1948-1957
      - Finances, 1952-1958
      - Form letters, replies to, 1952
      - Legislation workshop, 1954
      - Legislative Committee
        - Correspondence, 1952-1957
        - Reports
          - 1951-1955
          - 1956-1958 (Box 713)
      - Licensing law, 1950-1953
      - Listing of psychologists in telephone directories, 1955
      - Moratorium
        - Proposal abstracts, 1955
        - Replies, Alabama-Wisconsin, 12955, (5 folders)
      - Newsletters, 1952-1954
      - Officers of state associations, 1949-1958
      - Pending association, 1949-1957 (Box 714)
      - Policy and Planning Board Committee, 1951-1959, (2 folders)
      - Proposed bylaw amendments
        - Ballots, 1953
        - Correspondence and related material, 1947-1958
      - Psychology/Psychiatry relationship
        - 1951-1954, (2 folders)
        - 1955 (Box 715)
      - Public Information Committee
        - Chairmen, 1955-1957
        - Correspondence and reports, 1956
      - Publication releases, replies, 1954-1955
      - Reports, 1957-1958
      - State association membership, 1953-1956
      - Transition of Conference of State Psychological Associations to Board of Professional Affairs, 1958
      - Work charts, 1948-1952
  - Virginia Psychological Association (Box 716)
    - General correspondence, 1948-1976
    - Committees
      - Ad Hoc Committee on Organization, 1973-1984
      - Education and Training Committee, 1966-1976
      - Ethics and Welfare Committee, 1962-1976
      - Executive Committee
        - Correspondence, 1970-1977
        - Minutes, 1956-1977
        - Rosters, 1960-1980
      - Insurance Committee, 1968-1973
      - Membership Committee, 1966-1975 (Box 717)
      - Nomination Committee, election information, 1966-1977
      - Organization of State Associations Committee, 1962-1983
      - Policy and Planning Committee, 1961-1977
      - Professional Affairs Committee, 1966-1969
      - Public Relations Committee, 1971-1972
    - Subject file
      - Association of School Psychologists, 1968-1975
      - Blue Cross litigation, 1976-1977
      - Board of Professional Affairs, 1970-1976
      - Board of Psychologist Examiners, 1966-1974
      - Bylaws and constitutions, 1960-1974
      - Council On Health and Medical Care, 1960-1971 (Box 718)
      - Department of Vocational Rehabilitation, 1963-1979
      - Legislation, 1950-1974
      - Membership application information, undated
      - Minutes of membership meetings, 1956-1975
      - Psychological public services in Virginia, 1974
      - Treasurer's reports, 1965-1977
- Miscellany, 1931-1986 (Box 719-725)
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, agenda, transmittal sheets, receipts, forms, surveys, notes, ballots, printed matter, fragmentary material, notices, speeches and articles, testing material, and miscellaneous data.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, name of office, committee or organizations, or type of material.
  - American Association of Marriage Counselors, APA representative, 1966 (Box 719)
  - American Board for Psychological Services
    - Annual Report, chronology, and notes, 1959-1962
    - Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - American Catholic Psychological Association, constitution, n..d.
  - American Psychology-Law Society Relations with Division 41: Psychology and Law, 1981
  - American Public Health Association, 1966
  - Annual conventions
    - Agenda material, 1977, 1983, undated
    - Correspondence, 1977-1983
    - Minutes and related material, 1977-1978, 1983, undated
  - Antitrust litigation, chiropractors v. various medical associations, 1980
  - Archives, transmittal and receipt form, 1983
  - Articles, 1958-1980, undated
  - Association for the Advancement of Psychology, Special Projects Advisory Committee, 1980
  - Bibliography, undated
  - Board of Ethnic Minority Affairs, draft minutes of meeting, 1982
  - Board of Professional Affairs, agenda item, 1983
  - Brief, Nassau Neuropsychiatric Society v. Adelphi University, Garden City, N.Y., APA as amicus curiae, 1966
  - Calendars of events, 1983
  - Carnegie Corp., 1981-1982
  - Central Office, memoranda to staff, 1983
  - Committee on Local Professional Groups, surveys, 1963-1966
  - Committee on Psychological Tests, rules of council, 1971
  - Committee on Scientific and Professional Ethics of Conduct, 1975, undated
  - Committee on Women's Programs, Akron v. Akron Center for Reproductive Health decision, 1982
  - Conference of Psychologist Directors in State, Federal, and Territorial Mental Health Programs (Box 720)
    - Agenda and related material, 1972-1975
    - Article and speech, 1969, undated
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1967-1976, undated
        - Kiesler, Charles A., with Daniel P. Moynihan, 1978
      - Directories, 1969-1973
      - Notes on meetings, 1975, 1977
      - Perspectives, Mar. 1960-Apr. 1971, (2 folders)
  - Correspondence, inquires on various subjects, 1931-1947, 1961-1965
  - Defense of doctorate for clinical psychology positions, APA draft affidavit to Civil Service Commission, 1978
  - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
    - National Institute of Education, 1976-1982
    - Office of Vocational Rehabilitation, correspondence, Erasmus Leonard Hoch, 1959-1962, undated (Box 721)
  - Definition of "Psychologist," list of state laws, 1966
  - Diagnostic and Statistical Manual III, classification of disorders, 1970
  - Distinguished Scientific Contribution Award, nominees
    - Berlyne, D. E., 1973
    - Crutchfield, Richard S., 1970
    - Ghiselli, Edwin E., 1971-1972
    - Kluver, Heinrich, 1973, undated
    - Melton, Arthur W., 1974-1975
    - Teuber, Hans-Lucas, 1972-1975, undated
  - Educational credit, military experience, Army air forces, 1944-1946, undated
  - Facts About Psychology and Psychologists Project, 1972-1973, undated
  - Federal legislation
    - National Science Policy and Priorities Act, Edward M. Kennedy, 1972
    - Various issues, 1967-1983
  - Financial, 1962, 1982
  - Fragments, 1965, 1972, 1977, undated
  - Governance Affairs, meeting change, 1983
  - Information systems, 1970-1974, undated
  - Joint APA/National Association of School Psychologists Task Force, first meeting, progress report, 1979
  - Marketing Department, information request form, undated
  - National Plan for the Chronically Mentally Ill, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1977-1980, undated (Box 722)
  - National Research Council
    - Committee on the History of Psychology and the War
      - Correspondence, Robert Mearns Yerkes, 1943-1945
      - Federal Communications Commission, Foreign Broadcast Intelligence Service, 1944-1946
      - Meetings, minutes, and memos, 1943-1948, undated
      - Navy Department, Bureau of Naval Personnel, 1945
      - Notes, undated
      - The Psychobiological Program at the U.S. Maritime Service Training Station
        - Acknowledgements, contents, preface, and editor's note, 1946
        - Chapters 1-22, (5 folders)
        - Chapters 23-26 (Box 723)
      - Reports, 1940-1945, undated, (2 folders)
    - Committee on the Selection and Training of Aircraft Pilots, Oct. 1944-Nov. 1946, undated, (2 folders)
  - National Science Foundation, Institute on New Developments in Developmental and Clinical Psychology for Secondary School Teachers, 1980
  - Notes, 1975-1976, undated (Box 724)
  - Office of Communication Management and Development
    - Meeting agenda and planning material, 1968-1971
    - Summary of APA information activities, 1970
  - Organizational Review Committee, meeting plan, 1983
  - Papers, 1964, 1971, undated
  - Personnel Office, notices of position openings, 1983
  - Photographic transparencies, "Social Influences on Behavior," undated
  - Physically handicapped, Department of Housing and Urban Development project, undated
  - Project on Scientific Information Exchange in Psychology, 1963
  - Scientific Research Corps, proposal for, Army air forces, 1945-1946
  - Smithsonian Science Information Exchange, standard report package, 1971
  - Special projects
    - National Association for Mental Health, Role Relationships Group, minutes of meetings, 1976
    - National Institute of Mental Health, Conference of Chief Psychologists in State and Mental Health Programs, 1952-1964, (2 folders)
    - National Research Council, Assembly of Behavioral and Social Sciences, 17-18 Nov. 1978 (Box 725)
    - "The Place of Psychology in the University," American Psychologist issue, and symposium, 1969, undated
    - Task Force on Behavioral Classification, 1977
    - Task Force on Developing Standards of Professional Practice, mission statement, undated
    - Task Force on Education and Credentialing, Implementation Subcommittee, material for 3-5 Dec. 1981 meeting
      - Correspondence and related material, 1981, undated
      - Enclosures 1-9 and 11-13, 1981
    - Task Force on Psychology and Health Maintenance Organizations, 1979-1980
    - Task Force on Sex Bias, report to Board of Professional Affairs, 1975
  - Speeches and statements, various, 1963-1977, undated
  - Teaching Man-Environment Relations, booklet, 1974
  - Tests, 1976, undated, (2 folders)
  - Veterans, education and job opportunities, 1946
Index to Abbreviations and Acronymns
AAAP American Association of Applied Psychology
AAAS American Association for the Advancement of Science
AAP Association for the Advancement of Psychology
AAPCC American Association of Psychiatric Clinics for Children
AAUPTC American Association of University Psychology Training Centers
ABA American Bar Association
AMA American Medical Association
APA American Psychiatric Association
APA American Psychological Association
BPA Board of Professional Affairs
BSA Board of Scientific Affairs
BSCS Biological Sciences Curriculum Study
BSERP Board of Social and Ethical Responsibility of Psychologists
CAMAS Coordinated Application, Matching, and Admissions System for Graduate Programs in Psychology
CAPASAR Ad Hoc Committee on APA/State Association Relations
CAPPS Council for the Advancement of Psychological Professions and Sciences
CEOP Committee of Equality of Opportunity in Psychology
COFSA Continuing Committee on Organization and Function of State Asociations
COMDOC Committee on Doctoral Training
CONPASS Consortium of Professional Associations for Study of Special Teacher Improvement Programs
COPDAC Conference of Psychologist Directors in State, Federal, and Territorial Mental Health Programs
COPPIA Ad Hoc Committee on Promoting Public Interest Activity
CP Division 27: Community Psychology
CPOP Committee on Psychology in Other Professional Schools
CPT Current Procedural Terminology
CSPEC Ad Hoc Committee on Scientific and Professional Ethics and Conduct
CWP Committee on Women in Psychology
EAB Division 25: Experimental Analysis of Behavior
EAO Educational Affairs Office
EDRA Environmental Design Research Association
EEOC Equal Employment Opportunity Commission
ETB Education and Training Board
ETS Educational Testing Service
FIPSE Fund for the Improvement of Post-Secondary Education
HP Division 32: Humanistic Psychology
I & OP Division 14: Industrial and Organizational Psychology
JASP Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology
JCPP Journal of Comparative and Physiological Psychology
JEP Journal of Experimental Psychology
JPSP Journal of Personality and Social Psychology
JSAS Journal Supplement Abstract Services
LC Library of Congress